<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://friends.hermosawavephotography.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://friends.hermosawavephotography.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-01-28T17:57:41+00:00</updated><id>https://friends.hermosawavephotography.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Friends of Hermosawave Photography</title><subtitle>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The End of a Thrilling Year!</title><link href="https://friends.hermosawavephotography.com/members/empty%20kyoto/2023/12/30/the-end.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The End of a Thrilling Year!" /><published>2023-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://friends.hermosawavephotography.com/members/empty%20kyoto/2023/12/30/the-end</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://friends.hermosawavephotography.com/members/empty%20kyoto/2023/12/30/the-end.html"><![CDATA[<p>Well here we are folks! The end of a thrilling year, and the end of the publishing process for the Empty Kyoto book.</p>

<p>The idea for the book germinated in April of this year, fundraising started in July, the layout in August, printing September through November, shipping in December. And now we’re done!</p>

<p>Most all of you have received your books, although there are about a dozen orders still out there, notably shipments to Canada and shipments that went through New York City…</p>
<figure class="max-width"><img src="/assets/images/emptykyoto/409544665_10159980452783263_8257483572849494193_n.jpg" /><figcaption>(Photo courtesy of William Susman)</figcaption></figure>

<p>Now the book is out in the wild and I am seeing images like this one pop up on social media, which generates new orders as well. It’s a great feeling. Thank you.</p>

<p>I’m taking a small amount of time off, as everything in Japan closes down between ~December 30 and January 6. Our Osechi New Year’s meal arrived yesterday and is in the refrigerator. Our neighbor, a florist, is super busy preparing all kinds of New Year’s decorations and floral arrangements.</p>

<figure><img src="/assets/images/emptykyoto/2312_IMG_9226-7.jpg" /></figure>

<p>Thanks again for coming on this ride with me this year. There is more to come as I continue to promote the book and prepare for a gallery exhibit April 13-21 in Kyoto, as part of the Kyotographie International Photography festival. (More to come on this)</p>

<p>In January, I’ll be going back to California, followed by a trip to Seattle and Kansas to see my family, before returning to Kyoto in mid-March.</p>

<p>If you’re in the US and are interested in books or the 2024 calendars, I will be able to send them from California, saving time and money on the shipping. I have updated the website with the new pricing, effective until mid March.</p>

<p>I’m still experimenting with this newsletter and the supporters’ website, too. I started using Substack, which was okay, but I left because of their business practices. I moved to Ghost, which was also okay, but I wasn’t happy with their membership features. So now I’m using Memberful; here the membership features are good, but the newsletter/blogging features are lacking – actually they encourage you to host your newsletter and website elsewhere.</p>

<p>I want more visual control of… well everything. All of these sites, by appealing to people with no web design experience, lock you into such a generic vanilla look, like this newsletter you’re reading now. It’s boring.</p>

<p>I’ve also moved the online purchasing component from Square to Stripe. I love Square for in-person transactions and have used them since they first launched in 2011. I have also used Stripe on and off for many years. Stripe is more web-focused and developer-centric, so a little harder to set up, but much better for the web in terms of localized user experience. I have customers all over the world and Stripe just feels better.  I suppose something like Shopify might be the best online shopping solution, but I only have two products (the book and the calendar) and it seems like overkill to maintain a full blown online store. I already have a separate online printshop using SmugMug.  <em> It’s too much. </em></p>

<p><strong>So things are still in flux. </strong> (Just like everything else in the world.)</p>

<p>Recently, I’ve been doing a number of things with <a href="http://kyotojournal.org/" target="blank"><strong>Kyoto Journal</strong></a>, which if you don’t already know about you really should take a look at. A photo from Empty Kyoto is on the cover of the current issue, 105 and there is a feature about my book. I’ve been writing an article about Bagels &amp; Sushi for their  issue, Cultural Fluidity, <s>106</s> 108; and I’ve been shooting a lot of photos to accompany several articles in the following issue, Fire &amp; Kyoto, 107, coming in the spring. There are very few magazines devoted to Japanese culture in English, and I’ve been reading the magazine for years. I used to visit the Kinokuniya book store in Little Tokyo, Los Angeles, to get the latest issues. So it’s a privilege to be able to work with them now.</p>

<p>I guess that’s about it. Best wishes for a safe and enjoyable holiday and the best of luck in 2024. We’ll need it.</p>

<p>– Daniel</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Empty Kyoto" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Well here we are folks! The end of a thrilling year, and the end of the publishing process for the Empty Kyoto book.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Shipping Report</title><link href="https://friends.hermosawavephotography.com/members/empty%20kyoto/2023/12/08/shipping_report.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Shipping Report" /><published>2023-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://friends.hermosawavephotography.com/members/empty%20kyoto/2023/12/08/shipping_report</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://friends.hermosawavephotography.com/members/empty%20kyoto/2023/12/08/shipping_report.html"><![CDATA[<figure><img src="/assets/images/ek_images/f93a45390dfc8877359ff040e67f8ff6_original.jpg" /><figcaption><span>Shipping Boxes</span></figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Hi folks:</p>

<p>After 10 days, we’ve shipped about 2/3 of the orders. Any reward of more than a single book has already been shipped.</p>

<p>Tracking the packages, I can see that the first, most time-sensitive ones have already been delivered. The other shipments have either arrived in the destination country, or are through customs and waiting for a flight out of Osaka’s Kansai airport. For the US, “destination country” often means Fairbanks, Alaska, so it will take a few more days to get to you.</p>

<p>If I have shipped your reward, you will have already received an email with a tracking link.</p>

<p>I have been prioritizing USA shipments up to now, the vast majority of rewards. Starting Monday, I will prioritize UK/EU shipments. Shipments within Japan will go last, as most will be delivered the day after shipment.</p>

<p>I have plenty of boxes, but one thing that has become problematic is obtaining enough intermediate envelopes to go into the boxes. I’m going to have to get more creative with the packaging!</p>

<p>Anyway, you’ll get your books soon! I hope you enjoy them. And don’t be shy sharing photos on social media, I love seeing them!</p>

<p>Have a great weekend!</p>

<p>Daniel</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Empty Kyoto" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Shipping Boxes]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Books Are Here!</title><link href="https://friends.hermosawavephotography.com/members/empty%20kyoto/2023/11/30/book-are-here.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Books Are Here!" /><published>2023-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://friends.hermosawavephotography.com/members/empty%20kyoto/2023/11/30/book-are-here</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://friends.hermosawavephotography.com/members/empty%20kyoto/2023/11/30/book-are-here.html"><![CDATA[<figure><img src="/assets/images/ek_images/2311_A7R04887_sm.jpg" /><figcaption><span>Shipping Boxes</span></figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Hi folks:</p>

<p>A little update to let you know that the books have arrived, they are being packaged and shipped now.</p>

<p>The book looks great! However it looks just like all the individual pieces I have previously received, so my reaction was more one of relief than excitement, to be honest.</p>

<p>I’m hoping the get all the Kickstarter orders out within the next week.</p>

<p>Thanks for your patience.</p>

<p>Regards,</p>

<p>Daniel</p>

<figure><img src="/assets/images/ek_images/0d80af8b7c9d0d81db1f37e702f0f3b0_original.jpg" /><figcaption><span>Lots of Boxes</span></figcaption>
</figure>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Empty Kyoto" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Shipping Boxes]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">11/24 Update</title><link href="https://friends.hermosawavephotography.com/members/empty%20kyoto/2023/11/24/ek-update.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="11/24 Update" /><published>2023-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://friends.hermosawavephotography.com/members/empty%20kyoto/2023/11/24/ek-update</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://friends.hermosawavephotography.com/members/empty%20kyoto/2023/11/24/ek-update.html"><![CDATA[<figure><img src="/assets/images/ek_images/6367d16e27e8135ba09171a74b39d5ba_original.jpg" /><figcaption><span>Color dust jacket and b&amp;w inside cover.</span></figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Hi folks!</p>

<p>Welcome to the latest empty Kyoto book update. Thanksgiving is a uniquely American holiday, so in Japan things jump from Halloween directly to Christmas. And since the important holiday by far is New Year’s, all the Christmas decorations vanish as soon as Santa’s sled disappears over the horizon. So they like to get an early start on Christmas, and things are already in full Ho, Ho, Ho mode.</p>

<p>It’s been about a month since the last update, my apologies.  However, I wanted to wait until I had more concrete information to pass along. And now I have it!</p>

<p>The last remaining unresolved element in the book was the cover. My printer and I went back-and-forth several times before they achieved a print of cover that I liked. It was mostly color issues: <em>“It looks great on my screen, why can’t you make it like that?”</em> Those of you with any experience in print publishing are smiling right now, because color matching between screen and print is one of the main challenges of printing on paper.</p>

<p>Anyway, that was solved about two weeks ago, and after that it was “All Systems Go!” as we waited for <em>liftoff</em>.</p>

<p>Today I received notice from the printer that the books were printed and were in the process of being packaged for shipping. The books will be delivered next Tuesday, November 28! And then I get to send them to all to you!</p>

<p>Hundreds of shipping boxes arrived yesterday, and I need to pick up a few other packaging items so we can be ready for shipping as soon as the books arrive.</p>

<p>Weeks ago I sent surveys from Kickstarter via email to confirm your shipping address. If you haven’t sent it in yet, please do so at your earliest convenience. Orders without shipping addresses obviously cannot be shipped, and I will not be able to follow up until all the other orders are out.</p>

<p>Most USA orders will ship via Kuroneko Yamato/UPS. this means Yamato (Japan’s largest shipping company, I think) will get the shipments into the United States, then hand them off to UPS for  delivery. I’m not sure how this works into Europe or other countries, I’ll have to check. My test shipments to the USA took about one week door-to-door. The shipments are trackable on the Yamato website, and I think they will also be trackable on the UPS site. I will forward tracking information as I get it.</p>

<p>Within Japan, packages will go via Kuroneko as well.</p>

<p>I’m not sure how many shipments I can put together each day – somewhere between 20 and 50 per day. So it will take several days to get all the orders out. In the address request survey form, I asked if your order was a gift. The gifts will go first.</p>

<p>I think as long as orders are shipped by December 15, they should arrive in time for Christmas, so there should be adequate time. Hanukkah on the other hand is early this year, so I hope shipments will arrive by the end of the festival, but no guarantees.</p>

<p><em>So there you have it. </em></p>

<p>I am preparing for delivery on Tuesday in order to make the shipping process as fast and orderly as possible. I know it will actually be chaos, but I’m trying to control it as much as possible. 😀</p>

<p>Hopefully the next message you get from me will have your tracking number in it!</p>

<p>I am also planning this to be the last email you get from Kickstarter. I am going to transition to a new membership website, and everyone who backed the Empty Kyoto project will get their first year membership for free. It’s a way of expressing my gratitude for your support of the Empty Kyoto project.</p>

<p>The new membership website will offer discounts on art prints, calendars, and future books (if there are any 😅) as well as behind the scenes stories of my photographs and life in Japan. And maybe more…</p>

<p>Once again, my thanks for supporting the project and staying with me until the end.</p>

<p>All the best,</p>

<p>Daniel</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Empty Kyoto" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Color dust jacket and b&amp;w inside cover.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Moving Right Along</title><link href="https://friends.hermosawavephotography.com/members/empty%20kyoto/2023/10/20/movin-along.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Moving Right Along" /><published>2023-10-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-10-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://friends.hermosawavephotography.com/members/empty%20kyoto/2023/10/20/movin-along</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://friends.hermosawavephotography.com/members/empty%20kyoto/2023/10/20/movin-along.html"><![CDATA[<p>Hi folks, here’s the latest of what’s going on with the Empty Kyoto book.</p>

<p>Actually, things are kind of quiet right now. The eye of the storm, I guess.</p>

<p>I have signed off on the inside of the book, which means no more changes or approvals. The printer is “full speed ahead” on production.</p>

<p>I am waiting for proofs for the cover and dust jacket. I think I will receive them in the next few days. Update: I received the proofs yesterday. I asked for some changes to the color photo on the front cover (dust jacket). I think this will set things back a week, but maybe not. What takes the longest is the book itself - which I already approved - not the jacket.</p>

<h3 id="the-2024-calendars-are-here">The 2024 Calendars are here.</h3>
<figure class="right"><img src="/assets/images/ek_images/68c24983c3a5d95d8e7f20dc57d5fb13_original.jpg" /><figcaption><span>2024 Calendar</span></figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Some have been sent out, many are waiting to go along with the books. If you’d like one you can order at this link. Choose “Will Call” shipping and I will include it with your book.</p>

<p>I’ve acquired boxes, wrapping, and other packaging for both the books and calendars, and I think I have a configuration that will be efficient as well as visually appealing.</p>

<p>What I’ve mostly been doing the past few days is organizing the shipping itself. I set up business accounts with a few express shipping companies, and today I sent several test shipments to find out the following things:</p>

<p>How easy it is to ship a package internationally, can I do everything online or do I need to go someplace to fill out those multipart forms?
Is the actual price they charge me is the same as their price list?
How soon do they actually deliver?
For the past 5 years or so I’ve been using JP Post (aka “the post office”) exclusively. But JP Post’s service really suffered during the pandemic, the lack of flights made things difficult. The US Postal Service has also made shipping to the US more difficult and expensive, by removing services that used to be available and by instituting more complex requirements. I sent a package last month by EMS (Express Mail) that JP Post says takes three days; it took seven days. Still figuring this out. But I have another month to get organized, so I have time to experiment before committing.</p>

<h3 id="the-empty-kyoto-digital-book-pdf-is-out">The Empty Kyoto digital book (PDF) is out!</h3>

<figure class="right"><img src="/assets/images/ek_images/d32d5ce048f622a0eaf4162f23ec3acc_original.jpg" />
</figure>

<p>If you’ve got one on order, you should have received a download link. If you didn’t please let me know. If would like a digital PDF version of the book, you can order here.</p>

<p>Anyway, that’s it for now.</p>

<p>Thanks again,</p>

<p>Daniel</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Empty Kyoto" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Hi folks, here’s the latest of what’s going on with the Empty Kyoto book.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">10/7 Update</title><link href="https://friends.hermosawavephotography.com/members/empty%20kyoto/2023/10/07/update.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="10/7 Update" /><published>2023-10-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-10-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://friends.hermosawavephotography.com/members/empty%20kyoto/2023/10/07/update</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://friends.hermosawavephotography.com/members/empty%20kyoto/2023/10/07/update.html"><![CDATA[<p>Hi everyone:</p>

<p>Thanks again for your Kickstarter support. It’s been a little while since my last report, but there’s been a lot going on. So let me get you up-to-date!</p>

<h3 id="the-book-is-getting-closer-and-closer">The book is getting closer and closer.</h3>
<figure>
	<img src="/assets/images/ek_images/b9d48d97452921ed9eeae9a2215266a5_original.jpg" />
	<figcaption><span>Left: trimmed, folded pages. Right: the book mockup. Behind: 8 pages on a sheet, as the book comes out of the printer.</span></figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Friday, I visited SunM Color again. I received a printout of every page in the book, on the new thicker paper, trimmed and folded to simulate the actual book, from the large 8-up sheets it is printed on.</p>

<p>The thicker paper is not much thicker, but it’s a big improvement in the feel. And for a real book, the touch and feel is important, wouldn’t you agree?</p>

<p>As I looked closer, I was astonished at how sharp the images looked. I’ve been making my calendars (more on this in a second) for 17 years, using a short run print–on–demand process, and I’ve been very pleased with the quality. But this book is something else! Really sharp!</p>

<figure>
	<img src="/assets/images/ek_images/1df7942aae72e3367a4e4ff71f9f7543_original.jpg" />

</figure>
<p>Mr. Osaka from SunM also gave me a copy of the bound book mockup, exactly as it will be – but without any printing. I had already reconciled myself to the fact that the book would be not be all that large, so the final size is pretty much what I expected. It feels good, the cover is fairly solid, the pages lie flat. The many double-page photos in the book will look great. Then there will be the heavy, coated paper dust jacket surrounding it. I think it will be great.</p>

<figure>
	<img src="/assets/images/ek_images/6b2d365a897f7c719aa271f1927e4081_original.jpg" />
	<figcaption><span>Close up on the lay flat binding</span></figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Next is that final check, adjust a few photos, and finish up the cover. This should be done within the next week.</p>

<p>The digital PDF version is waiting on the cover. So after the cover is finished, the PDF version can be finalized. I think the digital PDF version can ship by October 20.</p>

<h3 id="return-your-rewards-shipment-survey">Return your rewards shipment survey!</h3>

<p>Speaking of shipping, I have sent the Kickstarter rewards (aka, the book ;-) shipping survey out to everyone. You need to return it (or all of them, if you received more than one) before I can ship your order. If you can’t find it in your inbox or junk folder, I think you can fill out the survey by logging into your Kickstarter account.</p>

<h2 id="2024-calendar">2024 Calendar</h2>
<figure>
	<img src="/assets/images/ek_images/68c24983c3a5d95d8e7f20dc57d5fb13_original.jpg" />

</figure>

<p>Speaking of the calendar, I am happy to announce that the 2024 calendar is also at the (different, on–demand) printer, with a much faster turnaround. I’ve been gushing about the book’s quality, but the calendar will look good too, same as last year’s. Not as good as the book, but it’s also hanging on your wall, not sitting on your desk, so the quality difference should be acceptable. I’m hoping to have them this Saturday, the 14th of October.</p>
<figure>
	<img src="/assets/images/ek_images/d08328d3e18dd4e00bb630783819dbbe_original.jpg" />

</figure>

<s>The international shipping situation still sucks, but if you order now, the two month voyage by sea will still get to you before Christmas. </s>
<p>The international shipping situation has improved. A lower price Printed Matter postal rate, by air and with tracking has reappeared as an option. As a result , most of the initial shipment of books arrived within 14 days.</p>

<p>Those of you getting a calendar and a book with your Kickstarter will get them shipped together by air. If you didn’t order a calendar on the Kickstarter campaign but would like one now, you can order at this link. You can select “Will Call” for the Shipping Location, and I will add it to your book order, shipping at the beginning of December. I am discussing rates with several of the international air shipping companies and should make a decision in the next few days which one I will use.</p>

<h3 id="more-about-the-calendar">More about the calendar:</h3>
<figure>
	<img src="/assets/images/ek_images/ef31337ee2f6fc9f53f6467df794962f_original.jpg" />
	
</figure>

<p>This year‘s theme is “Images of Japan.” There are photos from as far north as Akita Prefecture, to Miyazaki Prefecture in Kyushu in the south. Many of the photos are pastoral photos of nature, the better to look at all month.</p>

<h3 id="my-previous-life-revisited">My Previous Life, revisited.</h3>

<p>In one of my previous lives, I was a musician and beat box guru. Some things about my work in the 80’s have popped up recently:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>An album of synth tracks called Traces of Illusion features my recording of “Dewdrops.” This version was recorded for Oberheim Electronics, the synthesizer maker where I worked. <a href="https://spacetalkmusic.bandcamp.com/track/dewdrops">Listen here…</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>*An Instagram story by the Los Angeles Times talks about <a href="https://www.instagram.com/reel/CxtzhwtpPUH/">me and my work with Dr. Dre.</a> If you’re interested in the track that Oberheim used as hold music, it was track I created to demonstrate the sounds of the DMX drum machine, which I digitized and edited whilke working at Oberheim. <a href="https://soundcloud.com/hermosawave/dmx">You can listen here on SoundCloud.</a></p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>I’ve worked in a number of creative endeavors during my life. They have all been places at the intersection of art and technology; where new technology is used for creative purposes. My photography and publishing are just the latest manifestations.</p>

<p>Anyway, that’s that latest news. Hope you have a great weekend!</p>

<p>Regards, Daniel</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Empty Kyoto" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Hi everyone:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Revisiting Film</title><link href="https://friends.hermosawavephotography.com/members/behind%20the%20shot/2023/09/27/revisitingfilm.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Revisiting Film" /><published>2023-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://friends.hermosawavephotography.com/members/behind%20the%20shot/2023/09/27/revisitingfilm</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://friends.hermosawavephotography.com/members/behind%20the%20shot/2023/09/27/revisitingfilm.html"><![CDATA[<figure><img src="https://blog.hermosawavephotography.com/content/images/2023/09/2309_A7R01564.jpg" ><figcaption><span style="white-space: pre-wrap;">Slides on an iPhone light table, with a magnifying loupe.</span></figcaption>
</figure>


<p>It started when I moved to Kyoto. I began noticing people carrying film cameras.</p>
<p>Even with all the talk of retro analog technology making a comeback, you don&#x2019;t see it so much in Los Angeles. In LA, film has been dead for a long time. All the pros that wax nostalgic about the days of film make their living shooting digital.</p><p>But Kyoto&#x2019;s culture is different. Here it&#x2019;s about craftsmanship, and passing on those traditional techniques that seem endangered nowadays.</p><p>A few years ago I worked at <a href="https://www.kyotographie.jp/en/?ref=blog.hermosawavephotography.com">Kyotographie</a>, Kyoto&#x2019;s annual international photography festival. And of course, at a photography festival you&#x2019;re going to have a lot of photographers touring the exhibits. So there were lots of people with serious cameras hanging off their shoulders. But what was surprising to me was that half of them seemed to be film cameras. I was shocked.</p><p>That&#x2019;s what sparked my interest in something I left behind 20 years before. My photography blog has been going for more than 20 years now, and the <a href="https://hermosawavephotography.com/210/?ref=blog.hermosawavephotography.com">last post shot with film</a> was in 2003.</p><p>My first digital camera was a small Casio in the late 90s that took postage stamp sized pictures of less than even one megapixel. A dozen digital cameras later I&#x2019;m very happy with the Sony a7r3 I&#x2019;ve been using since 2018. And I&#x2019;ve gradually moved to prime lenses that don&#x2019;t zoom. To paraphrase Mari Kondo, I want things I use to bring me joy.</p><p>But gradually the idea of a film camera started looking attractive. I decided I needed to take a deeper look. As I researched, I realized that an investment of $1000 would get me a great 35mm film camera and a few lenses. So that&#x2019;s what I did this summer.</p><p>Size and especially weight are important considerations for me, so I wanted small and light. I decided on the Nikon FM3a, the final model in a series of small robust manual focus cameras Nikon made starting in the late 70s. Nikon had several film cameras in production when they shut down their ENTIRE film business in 2006. This model was in production until then, so it&apos;s one of the last film cameras Nikon made, certainly the last manual focus model. And even though it&#x2019;s the newest one, it&#x2019;s still 20 years old. The lenses are even older, 20 to 40 years old.</p><p>I went to Fujiya Camera in Nakano, Tokyo to look for this hard to find Nikon camera. I told myself, <em>&quot;if it feels good to me, I&#x2019;ll buy it.&quot;</em></p><p>I say that, because a couple of years earlier I took a look at a Hasselblad medium format camera &#x2013; one of the most respected cameras in the world - and it was so alien to me, I could not get to any kind of comfort level in the minutes I spent playing with it.</p><p>So I went to the camera store and inquired about this FM3a model. Although it&#x2019;s a hard to find model they had half a dozen black camera bodies to choose from. They all looked brand new. It was amazing. </p><p>So I picked up the camera. It was small in the hand, and much lighter than expected. I was astounded. Weren&#x2019;t mirrorless camera supposed to be smaller because the entire mirror box viewfinder system was removed? This camera is smaller than my mirrorless Sony. And the lenses? So much smaller than my Sony lenses &#x2013; and each was only $150 bucks! (my favorite Sony 35mm f/1.4 lens cost $1800!)</p>

<figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://blog.hermosawavephotography.com/content/images/2023/09/2309_DSCF9133.jpg" alt loading="lazy"  ><figcaption>
  <span style="white-space: pre-wrap;">Nikon FM3a with 50mm f/1.8 lens.</span>
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>I put the viewfinder up to my eye. I momentarily forgot how those old cameras worked. But it felt good, really good in my hands. So I pulled the trigger for the camera, lenses, some Fujichrome slide film, and headed out.</p>
<p>35mm, 50mm, 85mm lenses and the camera body &#x2013; all from the golden age of Nikon and all in practically new condition &#x2013; for a bit more than a grand ($1200).</p>
<figure><img src="https://blog.hermosawavephotography.com/content/images/2023/09/2309_DSCF9106-2.jpg" class="kg-image" alt loading="lazy"  ></figure>

<p>After my experiences in the past, I wondered, &#x201C;Could I actually shoot photos, in focus and properly exposed, with a film camera?&#x201D; The answer from my first roll of film was a resounding yes. I could shoot sharp images, properly exposed, even on unforgiving slide film.</p>
<p>The first box of slides I got back from the photo lab were great to look at, but revealed a major problem with this endeavor &#x2013; how do I get these images into my digital workflow? I&#x2019;m hesitant to spend another $1000 on a macro lens or a film scanner just to take digital pictures of the slides. So I spent $25 on a set of close-up extension tubes instead. That got me some images I could work with.</p>
<p>The second roll of film, I took to a lab that could process the film and scan it for me &#x2013; <em>on a CD</em>. Remember those? It&#x2019;s been years since any of my computers had a CD, but the lab offered to copy the scans onto a flash memory drive if I would bring one &#x2013; and I was thrilled they would do that for me. Something about Japanese customer service. &#x1F609;</p>
<p>So I got my scans. I opened them up in Adobe Lightroom and&#x2026; <em>&#x201C;Hey, these are much smaller than even my iPhone photos.&#x201D;</em> So the quest for good affordable scans continues. Sigh.</p>
<p>I&#x2019;m not sure where this is all going to lead. But besides making great images, one of the joys of photography is just looking through the viewfinder and pressing the shutter button. You don&#x2019;t even need to have film in the camera. Just the process of taking a picture is a joy. And that is one thing I&#x2019;m really enjoying with this camera, looking through the viewfinder and pushing the button. With all my cameras, really.</p><p>In the meantime, I bought an adapter to use these old manual focus Ai-S Nikkor lenses on my Sony digital body. <em>Ohhh, now this is getting interesting&#x2026;</em></p>
<p>More to come. &#x1F600;</p>
<figure><img src="https://blog.hermosawavephotography.com/content/images/2023/09/2309_DSCF9126.jpg" class="kg-image" alt loading="lazy"><figcaption><span style="white-space: pre-wrap;">Sony a7rIII with 50mm f/1.8 Nikkor and Shoten lens adapter.</span></figcaption></figure>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Behind the Shot" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Slides on an iPhone light table, with a magnifying loupe.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">9/25 Update</title><link href="https://friends.hermosawavephotography.com/members/empty%20kyoto/2023/09/25/update.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="9/25 Update" /><published>2023-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://friends.hermosawavephotography.com/members/empty%20kyoto/2023/09/25/update</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://friends.hermosawavephotography.com/members/empty%20kyoto/2023/09/25/update.html"><![CDATA[<figure>
	<img src="/assets/images/ek_images/8d460f212d07051803ad0a24b55298a4_original.jpg" />
	<figcaption><span>12 page test print</span></figcaption>
</figure>

<p>As is the case with much of the northern hemisphere, it’s the last half of September and still the daily high temperature approaches 90° F. It is getting cooler though. I came to Japan for the first time in 1984, right around this time of the year. I remember the weather being very pleasant, not like this year. Things have changed!</p>

<p>Last week I received a print of 12 pages of the book, on the actual press, on the actual paper. That’s what’s at the top of this post. The images look great, but we decided I should improve one photo and replace one of the others.</p>

<p>I also asked about using slightly thicker paper. It’s fine the way it is but I’d just like a little more heft to the pages. This will, of course, cause printing and shipping to become more expensive; but if it’s not that much more I’m going to go for it. (Update: I went for it :-)</p>

<p>I’ve also been working on the cover this week. I can finish the cover most of the way, but it can’t be completed until we know how thick the book is; and the paper change will change the book thickness as well. Change one thing, and it changes many other things. I think most people have no idea how complicated manufacturing anything is.</p>

<h2 id="2024-calendar">2024 Calendar</h2>

<p>I did a lot of prep work for the 2024 calendar last spring, anticipating a lack of time in which to prepare the calendar in the fall, which now seems to have been a good idea.</p>

<p>This year’s calendar theme is all Japan. I have about half the images set, but I’m trying to find a window for a day or two trip west of Kansai to acquire additional images for the calendar. Somewhere along the the Seto Inland Sea (Seto Naikai) area between Osaka and Hiroshima, but the weather and other commitments have conspired against me. Maybe this weekend.</p>

<h2 id="kyoto-journal-issue-105-is-out">Kyoto Journal Issue 105 is out!</h2>

<figure>
	<a href="https://www.kyotojournal.org/product/kyoto-journal-105-geography-of-myth/" target="_blank">
	<img src="/assets/images/ek_images/862fbd2b2b4ef7e01350833624a80d66_original.jpg" />
	<figcaption><span>Kyoto Journal Issue 105</span></figcaption>
	</a>
</figure>

<p>If you don’t know about 	<a href="https://www.kyotojournal.org/" target="_blank">Kyoto Journal</a> magazine, this is the latest issue of an English language  periodical going back 35 years, showcasing the arts, culture and history of one of the world’s great cultural cities.</p>

<p>The latest - digital only - issue entitled, “The Geography of Myth”, features one of my photos from Empty Kyoto on the cover, an article about the book, and several other photos inside. You can find out more and purchase a pdf copy here:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.kyotojournal.org/product/kyoto-journal-105-geography-of-myth/">www.kyotojournal.org/product/kyoto-journal-105-geography-of-myth/</a></p>

<p>All in all I’m feeling cautiously optimistic about things. The book is coming together. I have some viable packaging and shipping options. I made a shipping test to see how well, how much, and how fast my shipping concept will work.</p>

<p>Anyway thank you for coming on this journey with me – some of you for months, some for years. I hope all this effort will be worth it.</p>

<p>– Daniel</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Empty Kyoto" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[12 page test print]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Plans meet Reality</title><link href="https://friends.hermosawavephotography.com/members/empty%20kyoto/2023/09/06/plans-meet-reality.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Plans meet Reality" /><published>2023-09-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-09-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://friends.hermosawavephotography.com/members/empty%20kyoto/2023/09/06/plans-meet-reality</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://friends.hermosawavephotography.com/members/empty%20kyoto/2023/09/06/plans-meet-reality.html"><![CDATA[<figure>
	<img src="/assets/images/ek_images/2309_A7R00733-2.jpg" />
	<figcaption><span>Cormorant fishing in Arashiyama the other night.</span></figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Hi folks, lots of updates to share with you today.</p>

<p>I’m going to be sending two versions of this update: a short one to my Kickstarter supporters, and a longer one to those of you subscribe to my book newsletter. Some of you may receive both. I apologize for the redundancy, as I transition from Kickstarter to my own newsletter. You can subscribe to my newsletter here if you’d like:<br /> <a href="https://emptykyoto.hermosawavephotography.com">https://emptykyoto.hermosawavephotography.com</a></p>

<p>I’ve been in Kyoto for about 10 days now, and have met twice with the printing company, SunM Color. Yesterday, I gave them the data for the pages of the book. So the wheels are turning!</p>

<p>Thanks again to my friends for reading, finding typos and offering suggestions. The book will be better for your work on it!</p>

<p>So, back to reality. Even the best plans do not work out quite as imagined, when they are faced with the actual work to be done. As with many projects, we will have to accept a specification that is not exactly what I had hoped for, while managing increased cost and longer turnaround time. But the good news is, the book can be done at a cost I can afford, in a way that will bring me joy, and on a timeline that everyone will be happy with.</p>

<p><strong>Spec changes:</strong> I had to give up on the hard cover. What we are going with instead is a heavyweight paper cover, when combined with the inside paper glued to it, plus a full-color UV-coated dust jacket, should result in a fairly substantial feeling cover.</p>

<p>We looked at many different books SunM has produced in order to decide what kind of cover, binding and paper to use. One of the more impressive was my friend John Einarsen’s book, This Very Moment. it’s a very nice book of Miksang contemplative photographs by the editor of Kyoto Journal. Here’s the link to more information if you’re interested: <br /><a href="https://www.kyotojournal.org/product/this-very-moment/">https://www.kyotojournal.org/product/this-very-moment/</a></p>

<p>The printing cost will be about 25% more than I planned, largely due to the premium paper and the lay-flat binding. And shipping will be expensive. But I can put together the extra money to deliver the books you’ve ordered and I’ve promised. That will not stop me.</p>

<p>Delivery of the books to me should be at the end of November. That still gives me several weeks to get them boxed and shipped all of you for the holidays. Even including customs delays it should take 7 to 10 days from the time I ship to the time you get them.</p>

<p><strong>Note about import duty:</strong> Individual orders to the United States will not incur incoming customs duty when they arrive in the United States. It should be just like when you order an iPhone online: your phone ships by international express mail and arrives at your doorstep. Folks in Europe, I think you are used to paying VAT or other duty for products coming from outside the EU, and I expect these books will be no different.</p>

<p>My next concerns are 1) the cover dust jacket, and 2) how to package the books in a sturdy, premium way to be shipped. More to come on these topics.</p>

<p><strong>Kickstarter is quite stingy with your personal information.</strong> They only provided me your nickname. I guess that’s a good idea I guess. So soon I will be sending you a form to fill out with your shipping information. Watch for it, and make sure it’s properly filled out.</p>

<p>In two weeks or maybe sooner, I will be able to see a test print of some of the pages – on the actual paper, printed on the actual press, to confirm the color and what the actual pages of the book will look like.</p>

<p>For the online version, I’m expecting to provide a PDF file which will look great viewed on your large screen monitor, like an iMac.</p>

<p>Anyway, that’s a lot of updates. Thanks for following along! 😀</p>

<p>Onward!</p>

<p>Daniel</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Empty Kyoto" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Cormorant fishing in Arashiyama the other night.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Back in Japan</title><link href="https://friends.hermosawavephotography.com/members/empty%20kyoto/2023/08/25/kamakura.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Back in Japan" /><published>2023-08-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-08-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://friends.hermosawavephotography.com/members/empty%20kyoto/2023/08/25/kamakura</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://friends.hermosawavephotography.com/members/empty%20kyoto/2023/08/25/kamakura.html"><![CDATA[<figure>
	<img src="/assets/images/ek_images/2308_A7R00311.jpg" />
	<figcaption><span>Windsurfing off Kanagawa</span></figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Greetings friends, I am now in Tokyo for a week, on my way back to Kyoto.</p>

<p>Just as in many other places around the northern hemisphere, Tokyo is super hot these days. I am thankful for air conditioning and Kakigori (shaved ice). 😀</p>

<p>I finished the book and sent it to a few colleagues for feedback. The feedback I received was to add a last section about Kyoto as it returns to its pre-Covid normalcy. I was also asked to include dates for every photo, to better understand how things unfolded.</p>

<p>I wrote a piece at the end advocating for a more reasonable level of tourism, but this was not received well. So I am reworking it.</p>

<p>I think the photos are pretty much locked at this point. A few more English edits and I will be ready to pay serious attention to the Japanese text.</p>

<p>In Tokyo I bought a JR East Tohoku Pass which allowed me to travel all over northern and eastern Japan for five days. One of my goals for doing this was to take photos of various other parts of Japan for the 2024 calendar. I can’t say this was completely successful, but I did get a few good photos. And I learned a lot about the various Tohoku Shinkansen lines…</p>

<p>Now that the pass has expired, I have been traveling around closer to Tokyo proper. And I’ve been eating. Coffee of course, cold soba noodles of various kinds (perfect for this kind of weather), tonkatsu (port cutlet), a Showa Era sushi bar (like going back in time), and pizza toast. All good, some better than others, none of it very expensive.</p>

<p>Tomorrow I will go back to Kyoto and get on with finishing the last bits for the book. Thanks for your support.</p>

<p>More to come!</p>

<p>Stay cool wherever you are,</p>

<p>Daniel</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Empty Kyoto" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Windsurfing off Kanagawa]]></summary></entry></feed>