<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-01-17T04:50:27+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Friends of Hermosawave Photography</title><subtitle>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The End of a Thrilling Year!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/members/emptykyoto/2023/09/30/the-end.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The End of a Thrilling Year!" /><published>2023-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/members/emptykyoto/2023/09/30/the-end</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/members/emptykyoto/2023/09/30/the-end.html"><![CDATA[<p>Well here we are folks! The end of a thrilling year, and the end of the publishing process for the Empty Kyoto book.</p>

<p>The idea for the book germinated in April of this year, fundraising started in July, the layout in August, printing September through November, shipping in December. And now we’re done!</p>

<p>Most all of you have received your books, although there are about a dozen orders still out there, notably shipments to Canada and shipments that went through New York City…</p>
<figure class="max-width"><img src="/assets/images/emptykyoto/409544665_10159980452783263_8257483572849494193_n.jpg" /><figcaption>(Photo courtesy of William Susman)</figcaption></figure>

<p>Now the book is out in the wild and I am seeing images like this one pop up on social media, which generates new orders as well. It’s a great feeling. Thank you.</p>

<figure><img src="/assets/images/emptykyoto/2312_IMG_9226-7.jpg" /></figure>

<p>I’m taking a small amount of time off, as everything in Japan closes down between ~December 30 and January 6. Our Osechi New Year’s meal arrived yesterday and is in the refrigerator. Our neighbor, a florist, is super busy preparing all kinds of New Year’s decorations and floral arrangements.</p>

<p>Thanks again for coming on this ride with me this year. There is more to come as I continue to promote the book and prepare for a gallery exhibit April 13-21 in Kyoto, as part of the Kyotographie International Photography festival. (More to come on this)</p>

<p>In January, I’ll be going back to California, followed by a trip to Seattle and Kansas to see my family, before returning to Kyoto in mid-March.</p>

<p>If you’re in the US and are interested in books or the 2024 calendars, I will be able to send them from California, saving time and money on the shipping. I have updated the website with the new pricing, effective until mid March.</p>

<p>I’m still experimenting with this newsletter and the supporters’ website, too. I started using Substack, which was okay, but I left because of their business practices. I moved to Ghost, which was also okay, but I wasn’t happy with their membership features. So now I’m using Memberful; here the membership features are good, but the newsletter/blogging features are lacking – actually they encourage you to host your newsletter and website elsewhere.</p>

<p>I want more visual control of… well everything. All of these sites, by appealing to people with no web design experience, lock you into such a generic vanilla look, like this newsletter you’re reading now. It’s boring.</p>

<p>I’ve also moved the online purchasing component from Square to Stripe. I love Square for in-person transactions and have used them since they first launched in 2011. I have also used Stripe on and off for many years. Stripe is more web-focused and developer-centric, so a little harder to set up, but much better for the web in terms of localized user experience. I have customers all over the world and Stripe just feels better.  I suppose something like Shopify might be the best online shopping solution, but I only have two products (the book and the calendar) and it seems like overkill to maintain a full blown online store. I already have a separate online photo gallery using SmugMug. <em>It’s too much. </em></p>

<p><strong>So things are still in flux. </strong> (Just like everything else in the world.)</p>

<p>Recently, I’ve been doing a number of things with <a href="http://kyotojournal.org/" target="blank"><strong>Kyoto Journal</strong></a>, which if you don’t already know about you really should take a look at. A photo from Empty Kyoto is on the cover of the current issue, 105 and there is a feature about my book. I’ve been writing an article about Bagels &amp; Sushi for their  issue, Cultural Fluidity, <s>106</s> 108; and I’ve been shooting a lot of photos to accompany several articles in the following issue, Fire &amp; Kyoto, 107, coming in the spring. There are very few magazines devoted to Japanese culture in English, and I’ve been reading the magazine for years. I used to visit the Kinokuniya book store in Little Tokyo, Los Angeles, to get the latest issues. So it’s a privilege to be able to work with them now.</p>

<p>I guess that’s about it. Best wishes for a safe and enjoyable holiday and the best of luck in 2024. We’ll need it.</p>

<p>– Daniel</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="members" /><category term="emptykyoto" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Well here we are folks! The end of a thrilling year, and the end of the publishing process for the Empty Kyoto book.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Revisiting Film</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/members/behindtheshot/2023/09/27/revisitingfilm.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Revisiting Film" /><published>2023-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-09-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/members/behindtheshot/2023/09/27/revisitingfilm</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/members/behindtheshot/2023/09/27/revisitingfilm.html"><![CDATA[<figure><img src="https://blog.hermosawavephotography.com/content/images/2023/09/2309_A7R01564.jpg" ><figcaption><span style="white-space: pre-wrap;">Slides on an iPhone light table, with a magnifying loupe.</span></figcaption>
</figure>


<p>It started when I moved to Kyoto. I began noticing people carrying film cameras.</p>
<p>Even with all the talk of retro analog technology making a comeback, you don&#x2019;t see it so much in Los Angeles. In LA, film has been dead for a long time. All the pros that wax nostalgic about the days of film make their living shooting digital.</p><p>But Kyoto&#x2019;s culture is different. Here it&#x2019;s about craftsmanship, and passing on those traditional techniques that seem endangered nowadays.</p><p>A few years ago I worked at <a href="https://www.kyotographie.jp/en/?ref=blog.hermosawavephotography.com">Kyotographie</a>, Kyoto&#x2019;s annual international photography festival. And of course, at a photography festival you&#x2019;re going to have a lot of photographers touring the exhibits. So there were lots of people with serious cameras hanging off their shoulders. But what was surprising to me was that half of them seemed to be film cameras. I was shocked.</p><p>That&#x2019;s what sparked my interest in something I left behind 20 years before. My photography blog has been going for more than 20 years now, and the <a href="https://hermosawavephotography.com/210/?ref=blog.hermosawavephotography.com">last post shot with film</a> was in 2003.</p><p>My first digital camera was a small Casio in the late 90s that took postage stamp sized pictures of less than even one megapixel. A dozen digital cameras later I&#x2019;m very happy with the Sony a7r3 I&#x2019;ve been using since 2018. And I&#x2019;ve gradually moved to prime lenses that don&#x2019;t zoom. To paraphrase Mari Kondo, I want things I use to bring me joy.</p><p>But gradually the idea of a film camera started looking attractive. I decided I needed to take a deeper look. As I researched, I realized that an investment of $1000 would get me a great 35mm film camera and a few lenses. So that&#x2019;s what I did this summer.</p><p>Size and especially weight are important considerations for me, so I wanted small and light. I decided on the Nikon FM3a, the final model in a series of small robust manual focus cameras Nikon made starting in the late 70s. Nikon had several film cameras in production when they shut down their ENTIRE film business in 2006. This model was in production until then, so it&apos;s one of the last film cameras Nikon made, certainly the last manual focus model. And even though it&#x2019;s the newest one, it&#x2019;s still 20 years old. The lenses are even older, 20 to 40 years old.</p><p>I went to Fujiya Camera in Nakano, Tokyo to look for this hard to find Nikon camera. I told myself, <em>&quot;if it feels good to me, I&#x2019;ll buy it.&quot;</em></p><p>I say that, because a couple of years earlier I took a look at a Hasselblad medium format camera &#x2013; one of the most respected cameras in the world - and it was so alien to me, I could not get to any kind of comfort level in the minutes I spent playing with it.</p><p>So I went to the camera store and inquired about this FM3a model. Although it&#x2019;s a hard to find model they had half a dozen black camera bodies to choose from. They all looked brand new. It was amazing. </p><p>So I picked up the camera. It was small in the hand, and much lighter than expected. I was astounded. Weren&#x2019;t mirrorless camera supposed to be smaller because the entire mirror box viewfinder system was removed? This camera is smaller than my mirrorless Sony. And the lenses? So much smaller than my Sony lenses &#x2013; and each was only $150 bucks! (my favorite Sony 35mm f/1.4 lens cost $1800!)</p>

<figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://blog.hermosawavephotography.com/content/images/2023/09/2309_DSCF9133.jpg" alt loading="lazy"  ><figcaption>
  <span style="white-space: pre-wrap;">Nikon FM3a with 50mm f/1.8 lens.</span>
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>I put the viewfinder up to my eye. I momentarily forgot how those old cameras worked. But it felt good, really good in my hands. So I pulled the trigger for the camera, lenses, some Fujichrome slide film, and headed out.</p>
<p>35mm, 50mm, 85mm lenses and the camera body &#x2013; all from the golden age of Nikon and all in practically new condition &#x2013; for a bit more than a grand ($1200).</p>
<figure><img src="https://blog.hermosawavephotography.com/content/images/2023/09/2309_DSCF9106-2.jpg" class="kg-image" alt loading="lazy"  ></figure>

<p>After my experiences in the past, I wondered, &#x201C;Could I actually shoot photos, in focus and properly exposed, with a film camera?&#x201D; The answer from my first roll of film was a resounding yes. I could shoot sharp images, properly exposed, even on unforgiving slide film.</p>
<p>The first box of slides I got back from the photo lab were great to look at, but revealed a major problem with this endeavor &#x2013; how do I get these images into my digital workflow? I&#x2019;m hesitant to spend another $1000 on a macro lens or a film scanner just to take digital pictures of the slides. So I spent $25 on a set of close-up extension tubes instead. That got me some images I could work with.</p>
<p>The second roll of film, I took to a lab that could process the film and scan it for me &#x2013; <em>on a CD</em>. Remember those? It&#x2019;s been years since any of my computers had a CD, but the lab offered to copy the scans onto a flash memory drive if I would bring one &#x2013; and I was thrilled they would do that for me. Something about Japanese customer service. &#x1F609;</p>
<p>So I got my scans. I opened them up in Adobe Lightroom and&#x2026; <em>&#x201C;Hey, these are much smaller than even my iPhone photos.&#x201D;</em> So the quest for good affordable scans continues. Sigh.</p>
<p>I&#x2019;m not sure where this is all going to lead. But besides making great images, one of the joys of photography is just looking through the viewfinder and pressing the shutter button. You don&#x2019;t even need to have film in the camera. Just the process of taking a picture is a joy. And that is one thing I&#x2019;m really enjoying with this camera, looking through the viewfinder and pushing the button. With all my cameras, really.</p><p>In the meantime, I bought an adapter to use these old manual focus Ai-S Nikkor lenses on my Sony digital body. <em>Ohhh, now this is getting interesting&#x2026;</em></p>
<p>More to come. &#x1F600;</p>
<figure><img src="https://blog.hermosawavephotography.com/content/images/2023/09/2309_DSCF9126.jpg" class="kg-image" alt loading="lazy"><figcaption><span style="white-space: pre-wrap;">Sony a7rIII with 50mm f/1.8 Nikkor and Shoten lens adapter.</span></figcaption></figure>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="members" /><category term="behindtheshot" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Slides on an iPhone light table, with a magnifying loupe.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Saga Matsuri</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/members/behindtheshot/2023/06/12/saga-matsuri.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Saga Matsuri" /><published>2023-06-12T04:29:08+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-12T04:29:08+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/members/behindtheshot/2023/06/12/saga-matsuri</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/members/behindtheshot/2023/06/12/saga-matsuri.html"><![CDATA[<figure><img src="/assets/images/theshot/2305_IMG_8146-2-1.jpg" /></figure>

<p>May 28 was the Saga Matsuri, a local Japanese festival in the Saga area of Kyoto, north of Arashiyama. Many neighborhoods have local festivals like this, and of course there are the larger, more famous festivals like the <a href="https://www.japan-guide.com/e/e3948.html">Aoi, Jidai, and Gion Matsuri</a>.</p>

<p>Several portable shrines with a local deity inside (mikoshi) are taken out and carried around the neighborhood. Many residents and businesses offer drinks: water, sake, beer, tea; and in gratitude the members perform a dance with the shrine, rocking it back and forth and generally making a lot of exuberant noise.</p>

<div class="subimagegroup">
<div class="subimage"><img src="/assets/images/theshot/2305_IMG_8163-2.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="subimage"><img src="/assets/images/theshot/2305_IMG_8181-2.jpg" />
</div>
</div>
<div class="subimagegroup">
<div class="subimage"><img src="/assets/images/theshot/2305_IMG_8171-2.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="subimage">
	<img src="/assets/images/theshot/2305_IMG_8177-2.jpg" />
</div>
</div>
<div class="subimagegroup">
<div class="subimage">
	<img src="/assets/images/theshot/2305_IMG_8105-2.jpg" />
</div>
<div class="subimage"><img src="/assets/images/theshot/2305_IMG_8157-2.jpg" /></div>
</div>
<figure>
<div class="subimagegroup">
	<div class="subimage"><img src="/assets/images/theshot/2305_IMG_8148-2.jpg" />
</div>
	<div class="subimage">
<img src="/assets/images/theshot/2305_IMG_8128-2-1.jpg" />
	</div>
	</div>
</figure>

<p>Here’s a short video I shot of everyone dancing with the mikoshi.</p>

<figure class="kg-card kg-embed-card"><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/LtBFV2AIBPg?si=uzunrcJgopU3d0vE" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></figure>

<p>Notice how new people come and relieve the others holding the shrine. It’s really heavy, so you don’t want to hold it for too long ;-) But there is definitely a macho element to the festival.</p>

<p>The shrine also has lots of metal noisemakers which you can hear. The chanting doesn’t really mean anything, it’s just a way for everyone to stay in rhythm.</p>

<p>After walking and dancing around all day (I did not dance, but I pushed the mikoshi when they fitted wheels on it, in between stops), I had a nice Japanese dinner with my neighborhood folks, and lots of beer -  much more than I was willing to consume :-)</p>

<figure><img src="/assets/images/theshot/2305_IMG_2749.jpg" />
<figcaption>My neighborhood participants.</figcaption></figure>

<p>This was my second time participating in the Saga Matsuri, the first was before the pandemic. All in all, its a fun time, and a way to better know your neighbors.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="members" /><category term="behindtheshot" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Empty Kyoto</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/members/emptykyoto/2023/05/09/empty-kyoto.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Empty Kyoto" /><published>2023-05-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-05-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/members/emptykyoto/2023/05/09/empty-kyoto</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/members/emptykyoto/2023/05/09/empty-kyoto.html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/emptykyoto/2211_IMG_6756.jpg" />
Toketsu-kyo Bridge in Arashiyama, November 2022.</p>

<p>March 2023: the end of the Japanese school year, the traditional “Spring Break” of western countries, the elimination of quarantine protocols for vaccinated visitors to Japan, and the several-weeks-early blooming of cherry blossoms all conspired to create a perfect storm of visitors to Kyoto.</p>

<p>For a few weeks there were so many, many people, more than I had ever remembered before, speaking so many different languages; all converging on the hottest cherry blossom spots for their <em>Sakura Hanami</em>.</p>

<p>All of a sudden there were hour-long lines for restaurants that we used to just walk into. It became impossible to walk on the sidewalk sometimes. Every train ride became an exercise in maintaining balance while being pushed in every direction by the crush of people.</p>

<p>It’s not like visitors to Kyoto are something unusual; the city has been a top travel destination for more than a thousand years. And the locals have been complaining about visitors for a very, very long time.</p>

<p>But that’s how all of us got our first taste of the city, as visitors. Who am I to begrudge everyone else?</p>

<p>However, the frustration of trying to live everyday life with all these extra people made me nostalgic for the days of peak Coronavirus, when Japan was closed and everyone stayed home. It was so peaceful then. Except for the ambulance sirens, of course.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/emptykyoto/2003_A7R02988.jpg" />
I wandered around Kyoto taking pictures of scenes that would have been impossible, before or after. Have you ever been to Kiyomizudera when no one else was there? Only the temple monks have.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/emptykyoto/2004_A7R04106-HDR.jpg" />
I remember being at Arashiyama’s Tenryuji Temple in 2016, trying to take a picture of the famous garden and buildings without any people. I sat patiently for about an hour and a half, my shot composed, waiting for the moment when the ebb and flow of people would create an empty space for my photo. It never came.</p>

<p>In 2020, I had the place to myself and was able to calmly create the photograph in my mind:</p>

<p>My 2021 &amp; 2022 calendars included some of these images of an empty Kyoto:
<img src="/assets/images/emptykyoto/2021_Bamboo-2.jpg" /></p>

<p>But looking back on that time, I think this subject would make a wonderful book. It was a once-in-a-lifetime event, and as such is worthy of some kind of commemoration.</p>

<p>So, that’s what I’m thinking about these days, how to make a book.</p>

<p>It’s not like it would be technically difficult, I’ve been making calendars on my own for more than 15 years, and I am very familiar with the tools and techniques of print design.</p>

<p>My thoughts are more about printing and distribution: should I try to find a publisher or should I do it on my own? How many should I make? What size? A small paperback or a large coffee table book?</p>

<p>How many could I sell? One really needs to print over 1000 copies to make the traditional printing process economically feasible. How could I finance it? A Kickstarter type campaign seems the most obvious. Are there really a thousand people ready to kick in $50~100 on this?</p>

<p>So many questions… I guess this is going to be my “job” for the rest of the year!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="members" /><category term="emptykyoto" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Toketsu-kyo Bridge in Arashiyama, November 2022.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Making Some Moves…</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/members/behindtheshot/2023/05/02/some-changes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making Some Moves…" /><published>2023-05-02T01:00:51+00:00</published><updated>2023-05-02T01:00:51+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/members/behindtheshot/2023/05/02/some-changes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/members/behindtheshot/2023/05/02/some-changes.html"><![CDATA[<p>A few housekeeping updates to share with you today.</p>

<p>I’ve recently moved many of my online services, mostly to make myself feel better I guess. I advise other freelancers to “work with clients you like, and avoid the clients you don’t.” Now I’m expanding that to to the service providers I work with; I don’t want to support companies with questionable ethics.</p>

<p>First of all, I have moved this newsletter from <a href="https://substack.com/">Substack</a> to <a href="https://ghost.org/">Ghost</a>, a different blogging/newsletter service. You shouldn’t see any difference, other than the posts will look a bit nicer. This costs me money at the moment, but it provides a foundation for future growth. So far I’m happier.</p>

<p>My longtime webhosting company Media Temple got their start working with LA’s creative community, that’s why I liked working with them. I’ve been to their cool offices in Culver City, and to numerous events over the years. Two years ago they were purchased by GoDaddy – whose ethics and politics are not remotely aligned with mine – and since the beginning of the year have been assimilating MediaTemple into the GoDaddy <em>Borg</em>. So I’m out.</p>

<p>I generally find Server-as-a-Service offerings such as Amazon’s AWS or Microsoft Azure to be designed for the most geeky folks out there. They are convenient, but not easy to set up – <em>user hostile</em> comes to mind. 😀</p>

<p>This year I have been experimenting with the <a href="https://www.linode.com/">Linode</a> cloud computing service for <a href="https://hermosawavephotography.com/">my website</a>, and finally got comfortable enough to commit to running a server there. Since I’m in Japan most of the time now, I set up a server in their Tokyo datacenter; faster for me, but might be a bit slower for folks in the US compared to the previous server in Virginia. Let me know if you notice a difference. I’m still experimenting with this and might move to a California datacenter instead.</p>

<p>Finally is social media, where everything has been in termoil since Elon Musk purchased Twitter. I have moved to <a href="https://photog.social/@hermosawave">Mastodon</a>, where I have several accounts.</p>

<p>I am still <em>syndicating</em> my photos to all the legacy social media: Twitter, Instagram, Facebook, LinkedIn, so if you’re following me on those services, you’ll still see my latest photos. But I do not hangout; I pop in once in a while to check if anything needs my attention. All these social media have been banished to an older “<em>social media iPhone</em>” that stays at home.</p>

<p>I still think RSS syndication (using Reader, NetNewswire, Feedbin, or other RSS reading apps) is the best way to get my latest photos without visiting the website. My RSS feed is <a href="https://hermosawavephotography.com/feed.xml">here</a> <em>(this will look ugly in a regular web browser)</em>.</p>

<p>I’ve also been toying with the idea of delivering the latest Picture of the Day as a daily email, similar to this newsletter. Is that something you’ve interested in? Let me know, thanks!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="members" /><category term="behindtheshot" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A few housekeeping updates to share with you today.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Kiyomizudera</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/members/behindtheshot/2023/04/07/kiyomizudera.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kiyomizudera" /><published>2023-04-07T03:52:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-04-07T03:52:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/members/behindtheshot/2023/04/07/kiyomizudera</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/members/behindtheshot/2023/04/07/kiyomizudera.html"><![CDATA[<figure><img src="/assets/images/theshot/image-12.png" /><figcaption>Evening light-up event at Kiyomizudera Temple, including a blue beam shooting across the sky.</figcaption></figure>

<p>April 2, 2023</p>

<p>The other night I went to a special evening light up event at Kiyomizudera, one of the most famous temples in Kyoto. I always enjoy going there, it’s a beautiful temple with great vibes (one would hope so) and great views of Kyoto from the eastern hills of Higashiyama.</p>

<p>One of my ideas for going to Kiyomizudera this evening was to shoot a photo as an <em>homage</em> to this ukiyo-e print by <a href="https://japanobjects.com/features/hasui-kawase">Hasui Kawase</a> from 1933, shown below.</p>

<figure><img class="center, max-width" src="/assets/images/theshot/self-portrait-at-kiyomizu-hasui_1017x1500.jpg" /><figcaption>“Self-Portrait at Kiyomizu Temple, Kyoto” by Hasui Kawase, 1933.</figcaption></figure>

<p>There were, however, many people visiting the temple this evening. I think there have been more tourists in the past month than have ever been in Kyoto, even before the pandemic.</p>

<figure><img src="/assets/images/theshot/image-13.png" /></figure>

<p>Even waiting until near closing time when the crowd thinned out considerably, there were still too many people, all hanging on the railing I needed for my shot:</p>

<figure><img src="/assets/images/theshot/4393da94-0191-4bf7-8052-b823cc3c2684_2000x1125.jpg" />

<figcaption>I shot several dozen photos like this…</figcaption></figure>

<p>I tried holding still and made multiple exposures of the same scene, with the hope that I could make something useable from all of them.</p>

<p>When I got home, I stacked the best half dozen shots into a single Photoshop file; then selectively erased the people from each shot. Finally, a small amount of retouching and voila!</p>

<figure><img src="/assets/images/theshot/image-16.png" />
<figcaption>Final edited image.</figcaption></figure>

<p>It is cool how the scene has not really changed in the 90 years since Hasui’s print; however this building has been here since 1633, so Hasui’s print still counts as a <em>recent work</em> in Kyoto’s 1200 year history. 😀</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="members" /><category term="behindtheshot" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Evening light-up event at Kiyomizudera Temple, including a blue beam shooting across the sky.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Takao and the Kiyotaki River</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/members/behindtheshot/2022/11/06/takao-and-the-kiyotaki-river.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Takao and the Kiyotaki River" /><published>2022-11-06T03:26:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-06T03:26:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/members/behindtheshot/2022/11/06/takao-and-the-kiyotaki-river</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/members/behindtheshot/2022/11/06/takao-and-the-kiyotaki-river.html"><![CDATA[<p>October 22, 2022</p>

<figure><img src="/assets/images/theshot/ee8b0185-8ed6-4a60-a864-c2d74f0cccfe_1949x1300.jpg" /><figcaption>A branch of orange leaves in front of Jingo-ji’s main gate.</figcaption></figure>

<p>Japan’s borders have recently re-opened to foreign tourists, and I’m seeing a slow, steady increase in the number of western faces walking around. But 90% of the tourists are still Japanese.</p>

<p>Anyway, going out this morning I see a crush of people walking around. It turns out today is the <a href="https://www.discoverkyoto.com/event-calendar/october/saigu-gyoretsu-arashiyama/">Saigu Gyoretsu</a> festival in Arashiyama. Arashiyama is one of the top tourist spots in Japan so I do expect lots of people, but this is more than usual. Pre-pandemic levels of people that I have not seen in years. Our time of peace and quiet is over!</p>

<h4 id="what-to-do"><em>What to do….</em></h4>

<p>We decide today would be a perfect day to go to Takao, about 5 miles into the mountains above Arashiyama. There are two nice temples there, plus a river that flows down to the Arashiyama area.</p>

<p>If it were up to me we’d take a taxi up there, but my thrifty wife insists on taking the bus. Anyway, we arrive and… it’s just about deserted. <em>Bingo!</em></p>

<figure><img src="/assets/images/theshot/image-6.png" />
<figcaption>A stone with an inscription memorializing… something.</figcaption></figure>

<p>Jingo-ji, one of the temples at Takao, is well-known for its colorful maple trees; in a few weeks it will be super crowded. But today there’s only about a dozen other people in the entire temple grounds; we practically have it to ourselves. And leaves are already turning; still mostly green, but great for some early autumn leaves shots.</p>

<figure><img src="/assets/images/theshot/138286ac-4603-4d59-b934-244c247d7293_2000x1333.jpg" />
	<figcaption>Outdoor tatami dining tables along the river. Notice all the moss.</figcaption></figure>

<p>After walking around the temple, we have a lunch at a restaurant on the Kiyotaki River. There’s only one other customer as we sit on covered outdoor tables perched over the river.</p>

<p>After lunch, we start our walk down the trail alongside the river. The restaurant is essentially the starting point, so it’s an easy walk. I love walking downhill :-)</p>

<figure><img class="max-width" src="/assets/images/theshot/9b228ec2-4cd8-4ab1-9e71-4c671f504df8_1600x2000.jpg" /><figcaption>From a small stone bridge crossing the river.</figcaption></figure>

<p>The path hugs the bank of the Kiyotaki River, and crosses it a couple of times as well.</p>

<figure><img class="max-width" src="/assets/images/theshot/05f24c80-43a0-4d7e-97c3-e9f8f14cd68e_1333x2000.jpg" />
<figcaption>A cedar grove along the Kiyotaki River, straight as arrows. <a href="https://hermosawavephotography.com/914426/" rel="nofollow ugc noopener">One of my favorite spots</a>.</figcaption></figure>
<figure><img class="max-width" src="/assets/images/theshot/c81b1324-2763-4cf2-bb1a-c9534ef4d703_2000x2000.jpg" />

<figcaption>People around here love to make these balanced stone sculptures.</figcaption></figure>

<figure><img src="/assets/images/theshot/d8f09fcb-4156-4431-9cca-17613dbce4f8_2000x1334.jpg" />
<figcaption>A long exposure blurs the water.</figcaption></figure>

<figure>
	<img class="max-width" src="/assets/images/theshot/ddee272a-692d-4270-95d1-8bab17cda037_1600x2000.jpg" />
<figcaption>Along the Kiyotaki River</figcaption></figure>

<p>Eventually, the river path ends at a bus stop. At this point it’s either wait for the bus, or walk through a dimly lit car tunnel about 500m long (1/3 mi). We decide to go for the tunnel. Very echoey, only wide enough for one vehicle (there are traffic signals at each end, to change directions of the cars in the tunnel.) We turn on our iPhone flashlights so the few cars can see us.</p>

<p>The tunnel lets us out at Nenbutsu-ji temple, which we pass for another day, and we end up in the Toriimoto district, a small street of well preserved homes and businesses, with a larger vermilion red Torii gate at the top.</p>

<p>Another 15 minutes walking, through streets and the crowded Bamboo Grove in Arashiyama, and we are home again.</p>

<figure><img src="/assets/images/theshot/image-8.png" /><figcaption>Big vermillion Torii gate at the top of the Toriimoto district.</figcaption></figure>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="members" /><category term="behindtheshot" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[October 22, 2022]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Arashiyama Sunrise</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/members/behindtheshot/2022/10/26/arashiyama-sunrise.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Arashiyama Sunrise" /><published>2022-10-26T03:03:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-10-26T03:03:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/members/behindtheshot/2022/10/26/arashiyama-sunrise</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/members/behindtheshot/2022/10/26/arashiyama-sunrise.html"><![CDATA[<p>Septermber 6, 2022</p>

<p>/members/posts/</p>

<p>It’s 5:15 in the morning. After a summer in the US, I’ve been back in Kyoto for a week. Up early with jet lag, I look out the window and run out the door. It’s about a 5 minute walk to Arashiyama’s <a href="https://goo.gl/maps/Qu6fKeKshkoXnXjW6">Togetsukyo Bridge</a>, but when I get there the beautiful pink clouds I saw out my window are already gone.</p>

<figure><img src="/assets/images/theshot/image-1.png" class="kg-image" alt="" loading="lazy" width="1456" /><figcaption>Watching the dawn.</figcaption></figure>

<p>I decide to wait for the sun to rise. But where? I see some other local photographers over on the south side, west of the bridge. I walk over there and take a few shots.</p>

<figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="/assets/images/theshot/image-2.png" class="kg-image" alt="" loading="lazy" width="1456" /></figure>

<p>But both my <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/sun-seeker-tracker-compass/id330247123">Sun Seeker app</a> and my own eyes are telling me that - from where I am standing - the sun will not rise over the bridge or anywhere else interesting. It’s too late in the year for the south side of the bridge, and too early for the north side.</p>

<p>So I go back onto the bridge.</p>

<p>I stand on the west side of the bridge and face east, so I can get the railing in my shot.</p>

<p>5:41. The sun is starting to peek out from behind the eastern mountains (Higashiyama) on the other side of town.</p>

<figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="/assets/images/theshot/image-3.png" class="kg-image" alt="" loading="lazy" width="1456" /></figure>

<p>Okay. This looks promising. But it needs something else. I liked the photo with the man and his bicycle at the top of this post. There are joggers and bicyclists going by. I take a few shots. But what if I slow down the shutter speed to blur them a bit?</p>

<p>That’s when the guy on the motorcycle came by. Leaning against the railing, holding the camera steady, I shoot just as the cyclist gets into the frame. And that was it!</p>

<figure><img src="/assets/images/theshot/6300af40-daf0-4aa7-9996-ae04f4a841d2_2048x1152.jpg" class="kg-image" alt="" loading="lazy" width="1200" /><figcaption>Picture of the Day posted photograph.</figcaption></figure>

<p>For me, I usually know when I’ve got something special. I take a look, is it sharp? It is.</p>

<p>I turn around and take a couple more shots of the Katsura River in the morning sun.</p>

<figure><img src="/assets/images/theshot/11697b8b-acc4-4fa0-841e-226d5b9fe3d3_2000x1125.jpg
" class="kg-image" alt="" loading="lazy" width="1456" /><figcaption>Katsura River in the morning sun, from the Togetsu Bridge.</figcaption></figure>

<p>It’s beautiful in Arashiyama, but this will be the scene for another day. Time to go home and make some coffee.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="members" /><category term="behindtheshot" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Septermber 6, 2022]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">About Behind the Shot</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/members/behindtheshot/2022/07/01/about.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="About Behind the Shot" /><published>2022-07-01T11:27:19+00:00</published><updated>2022-07-01T11:27:19+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/members/behindtheshot/2022/07/01/about</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/members/behindtheshot/2022/07/01/about.html"><![CDATA[<p>In late 2002, I started a website for my photographs, <strong><a href="https://hermosawavephotography.com/latest/">Hermosawave Picture of the Day</a></strong>. My goal was and is <em>“to create one good photo each day.”</em> After 20 years of posting photos almost every day, there are over 3000 photos on the site.</p>

<p>For the first 15 years, until 2017, it was all about Southern California: the beach, the sunsets, the small town vibe of Hermosa Beach.</p>

<p>That changed in 2018 when I started spending approximately 60% of my time in Kyoto, Japan. Now there are many photos from all over Japan as well as America.</p>

<p>I also share the photos on Mastodon, Glass, Twitter, Facebook, Instagram, and occasionally Threads. These days however, I feel social media is out of control; monopolizing eyeballs, clicks and energy.</p>

<p>So the best way to subscribe to my photo updates is via <a href="https://hermosawavephotography.com/feed.xml">my RSS feed.</a> (Copy this address and paste it into your RSS feed reader.) You can <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/best-rss-feed-readers/" target="_blank">find out more about RSS here…</a></p>

<p>I started this newsletter in 2022 as a more home-grown alternative, to try to recapture some of the creative enthusiasm of the old days.</p>

<p>Right now, I’m going to share one story per month or so. Writing about a photo, where I was, how I shot it, what I was feeling; so you can understand and appreciate how the photo came to be. I also occasionally write about the art and tools of photography.</p>

<p>Once things get going, I hope to make it more like once a week; but I like to take things one one step at a time, so we’ll see where it goes.</p>

<p>Anyway, I hope you enjoy it! Let me know how I can make it better.</p>

<p>Best,<br />
Daniel Sofer</p>

<hr />]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="members" /><category term="behindtheshot" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In late 2002, I started a website for my photographs, Hermosawave Picture of the Day. My goal was and is “to create one good photo each day.” After 20 years of posting photos almost every day, there are over 3000 photos on the site.]]></summary></entry></feed>